<page>

<page-title>OpenMath technology for Algebra Interactive!</page-title>
<body onload="init()" bgcolor="white"/>
<div class="REG">
<center>
Arjeh M. Cohen, Hans Cuypers en Hans Sterk<br/>
Olga Caprotti
</center>

<hr />
<br />
<div id="wat" >
<p><b>What is Algebra Interactive?</b></p>

<p>Coursematerial consisting of CD-rom and a book.</p>

<p>Topic: undergraduate Algebra, first and second year university
Algebra, i.e, Groups, Rings and Fields.</p>

<p>It is developped by</p>

<p>RIACA,<br />
 Research Institute for Applications of Computer Algebra,<br />
Eindhoven University of Technology.</p>

<p>Authors are Arjeh Cohen, Hans Cuypers, Hans Sterk.</p>
</div>

<div id="waarom" >
<b>Motivation and Goals</b> 

<ul>
<li>Construct a new learning process with the help of modern means
and IC-technology</li>

<li>Support for teachers. Many examples can be used during
lectures.</li>

<li>Support distance learning</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div id="hoe" ><b>How
did we try to realize our goals?.</b> 

<ul>
<li>Presentation of the course via a webbrowser.<br />
(Non linear presentation, search and navigation tools)</li>

<li>Use of computer algebra system to perform calculations.<br />
 (`Infinitely' many examples, experiments by students, checking of
exercises.)</li>

<li>Annimations.<br />
(Examples that attract attention, motivate and explain.)</li>

<li>Multiple choice tests and open exercises with hints and
examples.<br />
(The student has possibilities to check his/her
understanding.)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div id="OpenMath" >
<b>OpenMath!</b> 

<p>The second version of Algebra Interactive! will be much more
flexible and dynamic by the use of OpenMath technology.</p>

<p>OpenMath in Algebra Interactive:</p>

<ul>
<li>All mathematics will be in OpenMath</li>

<li>The source files will be in OMDoc, (a form of XML)</li>

<li>Sources will be in a Mathematical database</li>

<li>Use of OpenMath server to connect to several back engines, like
GAP, CoCoA, Mathematica.</li>
</ul>

<p>&#160;</p>

<p>Some new features will be</p>

<ul>
<li>Better search facilities<br />
 OpenMath enables searches on formulas</li>

<li>One source many presentations.<br />
 Using XSL style sheets one can produce different output
formats:<br />
LaTeX for a printed document, HTML for a web document, ...</li>

<li>One source many documents.<br />
 Using XSL style sheets one can produce different types of
contents:<br />
 Courses tailored for the needs of the students,<br />
 Sheets for presentation in class,<br />
 Reference book for students</li>

<li>Better and combined use of the various back engines<br />
 Even in a basic course on Algebra on Groups, Rings and Fields
there is the need of several CAS.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</page>

