<page>
   <page-title>MathML and DSSSL Files</page-title>
<h2 align="center">David Carlisle</h2>

<h3 align="center">Copyright 1998 1999 NAG Ltd</h3>

<h3 align="center">The OpenMath Consortium. Esprit Project
24.969</h3>

<h2 align="center">Introduction</h2>

<p>This page introduces several files relating to parsing MathML in
an SGML/XML system, and DSSSL style sheets which may be used to
render the Mathematics to TeX or to RTF (For Microsoft Word, for
example).</p>

<p>These files are being released to <em>allow discussion</em>.
They are <b>not in final form</b>. In particular the spacing and
font choice is usually wrong, as so far most effort has been on
recognising the structure of MathML.</p>

<p>Comments should be directed at the author of these files, <a
href="mailto:davidc@nag.co.uk">David Carlisle</a>.</p>

<p>In the first section are several entity declarations for MathML
symbol sets, this is followed by a second section with the DSSSL
style sheet and supporting examples and scripts.</p>

<p>The individual files may be retrieved or alternatively you may
take a <a href="mml.zip">zip archive of all the files in the
directory</a>.</p>

<h2 align="center"><a id="entities" name="entities">Entity
Declarations</a></h2>

<p>These stylesheets were originally designed to work with entity
declarations derived from the text of the MathML1.0 recomendation.
These older files <a href="mml10ents.htm">are still
available</a>.</p>

<p><a href="mml101ents.htm">A new set</a> of entity files for
MathML, and some other common entity sets are now derived from <a
href="http://www.tug.org/applications/jadetex/unicode.xml">unicode.xml</a>.
The stylesheets will be updated shortly to match these new entity
sets. The new files are also available <a
href="mml101ents.htm">from this site</a>.</p>

<h2 align="center">DSSSL Style sheet</h2>

<h3>SGML/XML</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="mathml.dtd">mathml.dtd</a> DTD from Appendix A of the
MathML recommendation (slightly edited).</li>

<li><a href="mathmlx.dtd">mathmlx.dtd</a> DTD for a rather minimal
document type that supports displayed MathML examples interspersed
with text paragraphs. (This file contains the DOCTYPE declaration,
so needs to be prepended on to a file containing the document
instance. Probably not the best way of setting this up, but
sufficient for this example.)</li>

<li><a href="xml.dcl">xml.dcl</a> SGML Declaration for XML.
(Unchanged from the Jade distribution).</li>
</ul>

<h3>DSSSL</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="mathml.dsl">mathml.dsl</a> DSSSL fragment that
purports to render the elements of MathML.</li>

<li><a href="mathmlx.dsl">mathmlx.dsl</a> DSSSL Style sheet for the
elements of mathmlx.dtd. Includes mathml.dsl via an entity
reference. It also defines a few debugging functions, and functions
in the DSSSL standard, but not implemented in Jade.</li>

<li><a href="dblib.dsl">dblib.dsl</a> The library file from Norman
Walsh's docbook style sheets. <code>dblib.dsl 1.7 1998/05/06
15:04:0</code></li>
</ul>

<h3>Supporting Scripts</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="jmml.sh">jmml</a> Script (batch file) which given a file
as argument, calls jade with suitable arguments to process the file
to produce TeX.</li>

<li><a href="jmmlr.sh">jmmlr</a> Script (batch file) which given a
file as argument, calls jade with suitable arguments to process the
file to produce RTF. The RTF coming from Jade is further modified
by the small script below.</li>

<li><a href="rtffix.sh">rtffix</a> Even if min-leading is set, the
displayed math always appears in the rtf clipped to a 12pt `exact'
baseline. This script just edits it to be `at least'. It just
changes the sign of a number which appears before each display. If
you don't have sed, you can load the file in to word and alter the
paragraph properties of each math display to change the baseline
spacing.</li>

<li><a href="jadetex.cfg">jadetex.cfg</a> Some further
modifications required for the TeX backend. This requires a recent
patched TeX backend as distributed by <a
href="http://www.tug.org/applications/jadetex">Sebastian
Rahtz</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Examples</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="examples.mml">examples.mml</a> Some MathML.</li>

<li><a href="extex.ps">extex.ps</a> PostScript version of the
above, via TeX.</li>

<li><a href="exrtf.ps">exrtf.ps</a> PostScript version of the
above, via Microsoft Word.</li>
</ul>

</page>

