<page>

<page-title>Mathematical Markup Language (MathML) and the ESPRIT
OpenMath Project</page-title>
<h4><br />
Stephen Buswell, <i>Stilo Technology</i></h4>

<b>15 September 1998</b> 

<h4><br />
<i>Deliverable:</i>Information Dissemination</h4>

<h3>Abstract:</h3>

<i>This presentation gave an overview of MathML and discussed its
relationship with OpenMath, outlining complementary areas and
differences of approach. The talk concluded with a brief
demonstration of some experimental MathML and OpenMath
applications.</i> 

<h3>Mathematical Markup Language (MathML)</h3>

<h4>Introduction</h4>

<ul>
<li>MathML (Mathematical Markup Language) is a W3C Recommendation *
published on 7 April 1998.</li>

<li>The goal of MathML is to enable mathematics to be served,
received and processed on the Web.</li>

<li>MathML is an XML application for describing mathematical
expression structure and content. MathML has a DTD, a grammar, a
Usage Guide and default semantics.</li>
</ul>

<h4>Maths on the Web</h4>

<ul>
<li>Maths has a two-dimensional symbolic notation</li>

<li>Maths is notation and content.</li>

<li>The Web is interconnected, interactive and dynamic.</li>

<li>MathML aims at automatic processing, searching, indexing, and
reuse, and working and learning at a distance.</li>
</ul>

<h4>Existing Maths Markup</h4>

<ul>
<li>TeX is a de facto standard in the mathematical research
community, with a large authoring community</li>

<li>ISO 12083 maths describes the visual presentation of
mathematical notation.</li>

<li>The Semantic Maths DTD has provided a base for the content
elements.</li>

<li>MathML inherits from computer algebra systems such as
Mathematica and Maple</li>

<li>MathML and the OpenMath community</li>
</ul>

<h4>MathML Basics</h4>

<ul>
<li>XML Syntax - XML is the core syntax of almost all emerging Web
applications. One consequence is verbosity. This has implications
for tools.</li>

<li>Presentation Elements support encoding of mathematics from a
(mainly visual) rendering standpoint.</li>

<li>Content Elements support encoding of maths from a semantic
standpoint.</li>

<li>Interface Elements allow embedding of the MathML fragment in an
HTML, and in the future will support the required interface
negotiation.</li>

<li>MathML Examples - examples of presentation, content and mixed
MathML were shown.</li>
</ul>

<h4>MathML and Other Standards</h4>

<ul>
<li>TheISO12083 working group is looking at supporting the
inclusion of MathML</li>

<li>The MathML WG co-ordinates with the W3C HTML and DOM working
groups on issues concerning XML embedding, namespaces, browser
interfaces and so on.</li>

<li>OpenMath</li>
</ul>

<h3>OpenMath</h3>

<h4>MathML and OpenMath</h4>

<img src="mmlom.gif" /> 

<h4>The Goals of OpenMath</h4>

<img src="compat2.gif" /> 

<h4>Levels of Semantics in MathML and OpenMath</h4>

The semantics of OpenMath can be seen as both deeper and wider than
MathML semantics. They are deeper in that there is a more formal
definition of the semantics in the Content Dictionary (CD),
including a formal, verifiable type system. The width comes from
the CD mechanism itself , which allows extension of the areas
covered by OpenMath without modification of the base OM syntax
itself. 

<h4>The OpenMath Standard</h4>

<ul>
<li>Abstract syntax, recursively extensible tree of OM objects</li>

<li>OM 'symbols' represent functions, operators, variables</li>

<li>OM object has representation as XML, binary, ..</li>

<li>Nodes of the tree can be attributed. Attribute is an OM object.
Encodes contextual information not derivable from data</li>

<li>Semantics of an OM Symbol are defined by a Content Dictionary
(CD). CD specifies the mathematical semantics of an OM symbol: type
signatures ; mathematical properties (associativity ..)</li>

<li>CD defines symbols for a mathematical area : Integer CD ;
Linear Algebra ..</li>

<li>2 OM applications can communicate if they both process a given
CD</li>
</ul>

<h3>MathML and OpenMath Tools</h3>

<h3>Tools and Products</h3>

<table border="2">
<tr>
<td>Viewing Tools</td>
<td>WebEQ applet - Geometry Center Techexplorer plugin - IBM Amaya
browser - W3C DSSSL for MathML - NAG/OpenMath</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Creation Tools</td>
<td>WRI Mathematica Maple MathType</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Editing Tools</td>
<td>EZMath - HP STARS/JOME - Stilo/OVE/OpenMath</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Conversion Tools</td>
<td>AMS Latex - MathML - AMS/SIAM/Geometry Center TeX4ht -
Rahtz/Gurari (Elsevier/Ohio U.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

A demonstration was given in which, starting with a MathML
expression displayed in WebEQ, the expression was edited using
STARS and the WebEQ display updated. The same expression was then
pasted into Maple, processed and copied into Mathematica. Finally a
new expression was generated which was displayed using
Techexplorer. The purpose of the demonstration was to show the use
of MathML as a carrier format between mathematically aware
applications. OpenMath will perform the same function between
producers and consumers of semantically rich mathematical objects.
</page>

