<page>
<page-title>OpenMath in Publishing</page-title>

<center>
<address>Michael Feith</address>
<address>Springer-Verlag</address>
</center>

<p>Springer is one of the world leading scientific publishers.
Almost 500 journals and more than 1600 monographs are published
each year addressing the top segment in research and education.
More than 50% of this material explains mathematical concepts and
hence contains mathematical formulae.</p>

<p>On the other hand more and more material is also published
electronically either online or on CD-ROM. At the moment those
publications are, however, mere conversions of printed material.
Springer is thus very interested in enhancing its electronic
publications with interactive mathematics. This is an important
milestone on Springer's way to provide not only high quality
content but also leading edge technology to address that
material.</p>

<p>Additionally more and more activities at universities and in
research and development in industry generate a growing demand for
interactive electronic material. Virtual universities provide and
require genuine digital publications. Researchers become more and
more used to online material on the Internet and intranets.
Springer is anxious to thoroughly satisfy those needs and thus
enhance its market share.</p>

<p>Within this project Springer sees the opportunity to develop or
employ strategies and applications within the following fields:</p>

<ul>
<li>standardization of the representation of mathematical
objects</li>

<li>applications for interactive online learning and teaching in
mathematics, e.g. interactive books to demonstrate mathematical
subjects and knowledge in an interactive and dynamic way</li>

<li>hypermedia documents where data can be transferred into an
underlying computer algebra system, being computed there and
allowing the results to be displayed in the document</li>

<li>optimized search functions for mathematical objects within
mathematical databases, text and data collections</li>

<li>standardized and facilitated means for the information flow
between authors, publishers, editors and readers</li>
</ul>

These high ideals can be reached by pursuing the three sub-projects
stated in the workplan: 

<ol>
<li>IDA (Interactive Document on Algebra) - Algebra is one of the
basic fields of mathematics. It is taught to undergraduate students
in many different fields (mathematics, natural sciences, computer
science, engineering, ...) Its high level of abstraction
predisposes that area for the use of interactive mathematics.</li>

<li>SMASH (Springer's Math Active Server at Heidelberg) - Libraries
or compendia of mathematical formulae (<i>formularies</i>) have
long been a central tool to learners and users of all kinds of
mathematical skills. While Internet technologies are rapidly
expanding, so far very few formularies are available online.</li>

<li>Electronic journal - Springer's LINK server at Heidelberg
presently provides almost 400 journals online. Integration of
interactive mathematics provides significant added value to all
users but requires new steps in the production chain. The
experiences of SMASH will be the ideal basis to gain further skills
on that field. By the end of the project one prototypical journal
demonstrates the possibilities and requirements of the new media to
authors and users.</li>
</ol>

Finally Springer intends not only to provide successful products
and advanced technology but also to promote via those activities
the OpenMath standard. <br />
</page>

